Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records LSC.1434
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Corporate History, 1911, 1922-2007
  - Titus Alexander files, 1911, 1922-1969, undated
    - The Dawn of a New Day for the Negro, 1949 (Box 44, Folder 4)
      National Negro Business League publication which includes copies of its correspondence with organizations such as the Tuskegee Institute, the National Housewives League of America and insurance companies.
    - GSM Board of Directors clipping, 1956 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - GSM clippings, 1953-1956 (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - GSM and civil rights clippings (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - MLK Jr. file, 1964-1969 (Box 44, Folder 8)
      Materials include copies of Letter from a Birmingham Jail, The SCLC Story in Words and Pictures, Martin Luther King, Jr. General Hospital "Focus" newsletter, MLK General Hospital pamphlets, Research Institute Report, MLK Jr.'s Strength to Love book jacket and a photo of King signing this book.
    - National Association of Colored Women Hand Book, 1952 (Box 44, Folder 9)
      The National Association of Colored Women, Inc. (NACW) is a "...fellowship of Colored Women united for service in lifting the standard of the home, and extending their service to help make better communities in which to live." The NACW was organized in Washington D.C. in July, 1896 when the National Federation of Afro-American Women merged with the Colored Women's League of Washington, D.C. and Mary Church Terrell was elected President.
      This hand book includes a foreword from President Ella P. Stewart, a prayer, historical notes, a list of past presidents, forms, the national song, a map of regions, an organization chart, a club song and objectives.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1911 (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Negro business clippings, 1946-1952 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Negro authors clippings, 1948-1952 (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Negro churches clippings, 1949-1951 (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Negro finance clippings, 1948-1951 (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Negro medicine publications and clippings, 1943-1947 (Box 45, Folder 5-6)
      Publications include The Untouchables, The Infantile Paralysis Fight at Tuskegee, and Progress and Portents for the Negro in Medicine.
    - Negro musicians clippings (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - The Official California Negro Directory, 1943 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Photostats of Japanese surrender, 1945 (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Pittsburgh Courier clippings, 1950-1955 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - P.A.N.D.A. program, 1956 February 24 (Box 46, Folder 2)
      Materials include two Productive Artists New Developments Association (P.A.N.D.A.) programs for its First Annual Installation of Officers Banquet held at the GSM Home Office building.
    - Prominent African American bio sketches (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Racial tensions publications and clippings (Box 46, Folder 4-5)
      Publications include Police Action in Minority Problems, Despite Discrimination: Some Aspects of Negro Life in the United States of America, An Idea to Win the World, Race Tensions and Equal Justice Under Law.
    - Edith Sampson clippings, 1951-1952 (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - The SCLC Story, 1964 (Box 46, Folder 7)
    - Library Catalog (Box 47)
      A wooden box contains the card catalog for the Titus Alexander Collection of Negro Life and History.
  - Almena Lomax files, 1970, 1973-1977
    Long time civil rights activist and journalist, Almena Lomax, graduated from Jordan High School in Los Angeles, studied journalism for a year and a half at Los Angeles City College, and worked for Charlotta A. Bass at the California Eagle, a black weekly. She left the Eagle in 1940 and started the Los Angeles Tribune in 1941 with $100 she borrowed from her future father in law, Lucius W. Lomax, Sr. After her divorce, she closed the doors to the Tribune in 1960 and moved to Tuskegee, Alabama with her children to cover the civil rights movement. After her return to Los Angeles, she was hired in 1974 by GSM to write a book that would document its corporate history. Her daughter Mia D. Lomax, who holds a Master's degree in history, assisted her with the research. While working on the GSM book, Insurers of the Dream: The Story of a People and Their Business, she filed a class-action discrimination suit against the Los Angeles Times and Times Mirror based on the claim that she had been denied a job as a reporter because of her race and lack of a college degree.
    These files include correspondence between Lomax and GSM executives, multiple drafts annotated by Lomax and multiple drafts of a GSM corporate history entitled "Once Upon A Farm" written by Dr. Doyce Nunis.
    - Corporate history notes and memo, 1970 July 16, 1973 March 28 (Box 48, Folder 1)
      Materials include notes from a conference with "Dick" Trueblood concerning his experiences in compiling material for the history of Occidental Life Insurance Company and a memo from George A. Beavers, Jr. regarding corporate history of the Board of Directors.
    - Nickerson material, 1974-1977 (Box 48, Folder 2)
      Materials include correspondence from William Nickerson, Jr.'s daughter, Quincella Nickerson Kimbrough concerning the omission of her father's name as Founder of Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company. She attached numerous annotated articles, GSM advertisements and publicity materials as evidence and sent copies of this letter to Ivan J. Houston, Larkin Teasley, George A. Beavers, Jr. and Almena Lomax. Materials also include letters from George A. Beavers, Jr. and Ivan J. Houston in response to Victor Nickerson's recommendations at the Annual Meeting. Beavers devotes the majority of the letter expressing his disagreement with Nickerson's recommendation that the term "co-founder" be eliminated. Houston's letter explains that he knows that William Nickerson, Jr. is the Founder of Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company.
    - Lomax correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box 48, Folder 3)
      Letters between Almena Lomax and GSM executives and employees such as Ivan J. Houston, Norman O. Houston, Mabel Cleveland and George A. Beavers, Jr. concerning revisions to the corporate history, Lomax's concerns over the delayed publication of the final draft and the historical inaccuracies of Dr. Doyce Nunis' rewrites and Lomax's fear that her authorship may be removed based on GSM's relationship with the Los Angeles Times.
    - Notes and correspondence, 1976, 1977 (Box 48, Folder 4)
      Materials include notes from a corporate history conference with Dr. Doyce Nunis, minutes from a corporate history committee meeting and a letter from Almena Lomax to George A. Beavers, Jr. that begins, "I guess you're going to be able to comb me out of your hair with reference to the GSM history."
    - Insurers of the Dream: The Story of a People and Their Business (Box 48, Folder 5)
      Original "History Copy" of Almena Lomax's GSM corporate history. This copy is heavily annotated and its title page describes it as "A Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company Half Century anniversary publication."
    - Insurers of the Dream - Original (Box 48, Folder 6-7)
    - Insurers of the Dream (Box 49, Folder 1)
      The folder annotations describe this draft as "Original History Book 1 to Book Twelve."
    - GSM History - Lomax (Box 49, Folder 2)
      Materials include a photocopy of a draft with a post it note from Ivan J. Houston on the title page which reads, "This goes back to the Vault."
    - Insurers of the Dream - Chapters and letters (Box 49, Folder 3)
      Materials include drafts of Chapter 27, 31, 34, 40 and 42 and correspondence from the author, Almena Lomax to GSM President and Chief Executive Officer Ivan J. Houston. Lomax closes her first letter with, "I look forward to our meeting after you have received and reviewed my corrections. I will be wearing my boxing gloves."
    - Insurers of the Dream - Reviewed by I. J. Houston, 1975 July (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - Insurers of the Dream - Reviewed by I. J. Houston, 1975 December (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Insurers of the Dream - 2nd draft (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Insurers of the Dream - Extra Chapter 16, 1975 December (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - "Once Upon a Farm" (Box 50, Folder 4)
      "Once Upon a Farm" is the title of Chapter 1 of this rewrite of GSM's corporate history. There is no author named on this draft which includes handwritten edits and notations.
    - "Once Upon a Farm" draft, 1977 February 1 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - "Once Upon a Farm" - final script, 1977 February 1 (Box 51, Folder 2)
      This revision of GSM's corporate history indicates that the beginning and the ending were rewritten by GSM Public Relations staff.
    - "Once Upon a Farm" - N. O. H. copy, 1977 August 1, 1977 September 16 (Box 51, Folder 3)
      This corporate history draft was edited by Dr. Nunis and includes a letter from Almena Lomax to Ivan J. Houston. Lomax inquires about when the final manuscript will be sent to her for review, compensation for additional work she did on the history and concerns about the delay in preparing the book for publication.
    - "Once Upon a Farm" - Dr. Nunis edits, 1977 August 1 (Box 51, Folder 4)
      Materials include another draft of the GSM corporate history as edited by Dr. Nunis, a letter from Nunis to Ivan J. Houston, a list of GSM Board Members from 1925-1971 and additional correspondence from Almena Lomax.
    - Dr. Nunis' copy of the original (Box 51, Folder 5-6)
      Dr. Doyce Nunis' copy of Almena Lomax's original, Insurers of the Dream includes minor edits and annotations in pencil.
    - History Conference notes, 1973-1977 (Box 52, Folder 1)
      Materials include notes on corporate history conferences and meetings of the corporate history committee. These conferences and meetings were attended by George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman O. Houston, Ivan J. Houston, Edgar J. Johnson, Verna A. Hickman, William E. Pajaud, Ernest Shell and on occasion, consultant Professor Doyce Nunis.
    - "Once Upon a Farm", 1977 November 9 (Box 52, Folder 2)
      Materials include a draft annotated with revisions, a "latest copy of history" memo from Mabel Cleveland and booklets on the GSM murals and art collection.
    - "Once Upon a Farm" - final (Box 52, Folder 3)
      Dr. Nunis' copy of Once Upon A Farm includes handwritten annotations in pencil.
    - "Once Upon a Farm" (Box 53, Folder 1)
      This draft includes a few revisions in pencil and pen and an accompanying sheet of page numbers where these edits appear.
    - Company History (Box 53, Folder 2-3)
      Materials include multiple copies of "A Brief History of the Founding and Development of Golden State Mutual Life," clippings and photos.
    - GSM History (Box 53, Folder 4)
      Materials include a two page GSM history entitled "About Us," financials, locations and a list of officers.
    - The Founding of GSM (Box 53, Folder 5)
      Materials include the following three GSM corporate histories: The Founding of Golden State Mutual, The Founding and Development of Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company and Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company: Its History in Northern California.
    - GSM History notes (Box 53, Folder 6)
      This file contains handwritten notes on Home and District Offices by GSM's first employee, Helen Batiste. Her notes include names, dates and addresses.
  - Photographs, 1925-2007
    Photographs were arranged based on labels created by the company. Numerous boxes also include negatives.
    - Historic photos, 1925-1979 (Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56, Box 57)
      Historic photos is the company term for images that capture the foundation of GSM and historic events and visitors.
      Box 53: Materials include photos of William Nickerson, Jr., George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman O. Houston, Edgar J. Johnson, Bertha B. Nickerson, Helen E. Hodge (Batiste), Verna A. Hickman and GSM visitors such as Los Angeles Mayor Fletcher Bowron, City Councilman Kenneth Hahn, Architect Paul R. Williams and Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce President A.J. Gock. Materials also include photos of the Nickerson bust by sculptor Richmond Barthe, GSM officers and painter Betsy Graves Reyneau at an exhibit of her portraits of prominent African Americans. Additional photos include images of the following: Old Line Legal Reserve Permits, Conversion Honor Roll, 7th War Bond Purchase, policyowners accepting claim settlements and the William Nickerson, Jr. funeral.
      Box 54: Photos include images of William Nickerson, Jr., George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman O. Houston, Ivan J. Houston, Larkin Teasley, Stephen A. Johns, policyowners, Los Angeles mortuaries, Home Office buildings, Black insurance pioneers, Home Office groundbreakings, Congressman Andrew Young, Assemblywoman Theresa Hughes, Los Angeles Mayor Sam Yorty, Joe Louis, Assemblyman Fred Roberts, Madame Pandit, Congressman Ronald Dellums, Supervisor Leonard Roach, Dr. Ralph Bunche, Los Angeles Mayor Fletcher Bowron, California Governor Goodwin Knight, Lionel Hampton, Dick Gregory, Forest Whitaker, Paul R. Williams and Los Angeles Mayor Tom Bradley.
      Box 55: Materials include oversize photos of William Nickerson, Jr., George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman O. Houston, Ivan J. Houston, Home Office building on Western and Adams, Edgar J. Johnson, Tenth Annual Superintendent's Conference, Jessie Owens, Grace Means, Helen E. Hodge (Batiste), Simon P. Johnson, All Year Awards ceremonies, Home Office activities and a collage of prominent figures such as Sammy Davis, Jr., Martin Luther King, Jr., Jesse Jackson and Lena Horne.
      Box 56: Materials include oversize photos of the National Insurance Association 38th Annual Session, the National Negro Insurance Association Convention 30th Annual Session, the Third Annual Ye Old Rams Club Training Table Dinner at the Biltmore Hotel, the 6th Annual Rams Club Kick-Off Dinner at the Beverly Hills Hilton, the Interdependence Banquet at the Ambassador Hotel and GSM Home Office employees at the Adams and Western construction site.
      Box 57: Negatives include images of California History Tour with Charles Alston, Home Office buildings, R.C. Owens, Christmas party, Norman O. Houston at work, open house cocktail party, NAACP group photos, First Street and Los Angeles Street, Mrs. M.A. Hodgkins, Home Office construction, Peter "Nigger" Johnson, Jose Mascarel and Ralph Bunche's visit to the new Home Office building.
    - Home Office photos, 1925-2001 (Box 58, Box 59, Box 60, Box 61, Box 62, Box 63, Box 64, Box 65, Box 66, Box 67, Box 68)
      Golden State began operations in 1925 within a 12-by-14-foot second-floor office at 1435 Central Avenue. Seventy-nine days later the Company moved to the larger store-front quarters at 3512 Central Avenue. Groundbreaking ceremonies for the Company's first Home Office Building were held on August 7, 1928. This 2-story building was located at 4111 Central Avenue. Golden State's final Home Office Building at the corner of Western and Adams was dedicated in 1949.
      Home Office photos is the company term for images that capture buildings, executives, employees, visitors and activities at the GSM corporate headquarters in Los Angeles.
      Box 58: Photo plaques include images of the Western and Adams Home Office construction site and George A. Beavers, Jr.
      Box 59: Mounted photos include images of the 3512 Central Avenue Home Office exterior, Jesse Owens and employees in front of the 4111 Central Avenue Home Office (signed "Best of Luck Verna, Jesse Owens") and images of leaders such as Verna Hickman, Helen E. Batiste, William Nickerson, Jr., George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman O. Houston and Ivan J. Houston.
      Box 60: Oversize photos include images of Norman O. Houston and Lena Horne, Founder William Nickerson, Jr. and Co-Founders Houston and Beavers, Western and Adams Home Office Building construction, President Edgar J. Johnson, the Printing Department, Bertha Nickerson, Helen E. Batiste, the Board of Directors and interior office spaces.
      Box 61: Photos include images of employees working, Helen E. Batiste dancing, the Printing Department, office building exteriors, 1999 West Adams groundbreaking, building exterior architectural renderings, interior views of office at 4261 South Central Avenue and the Western and Adams open house.
      Box 62: Photos include images of Home Office open house, William Nickerson, Jr. bust dedication, cornerstone laying and dedication ceremony, 4261 South Central Avenue moving day, President and Chief Operating Officer Larkin Teasley, the murals, co-founder Norman O. Houston, the art collection, Home Office employees, Mayor Tom Bradley, Councilman Ernani Bernardi, Leonard Beavers, Leonard Grimes, Norman B. Houston, Supervisor Kenneth Hahn, Hale Woodruff, William E. Pajaud, football player Willie Davis and Ivan J. Houston, GSM computers, Menlo Avenue elementary class visit and Los Angeles Beautiful student poster contest.
      Box 63: Materials include photo albums presented to Board Chairman Norman O. Houston and Board Member Edgar J. Johnson at a Special Assembly in the Home Office Auditorium on November 12, 1970. This album includes a program from the assembly and includes group photos of GSM associates from Los Angeles District Offices 1112 and 1113, Compton, Chicago and San Francisco.
      Box 64: Photos include images of Operations Committee formation, Western and Adams newspaper stand, Certificates of Contribution, 24th Street School mural, Home Office interiors and exteriors, GSM Minority Foundation members, Underwriting Department, Officers and Central Administration staff, Adams and Western construction, employee of the month and an Olympic Torch runner passing by the 1999 West Adams building.
      Box 65: Photos include images of Founder William Nickerson, Jr. with co-founders George A. Beavers, Jr. and Norman O. Houston, Stanley Mosk addressed to Norman O. Houston and signed by Mosk, Reverend and Mrs. Abernathy, Titus Alexander and family members. Materials also include a framed photo of George A. Beavers, Jr., Mayor Tom Bradley and Supervisor Kenneth Hahn at a Los Angeles City Council meeting.
      Box 66: Photos include images of Richmond Barthe, Joe E. Brown, Alice Gafford, Althea Gibson, P'lla Mills, Clarence Muse, Liberia's Assistant Secretary of Defense D. Caesar Harris, Langston Hughes, Chairman Ivan J. Houston, Jesse Jackson, Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., Freedom Rally, Eloise Kloke, Herschel Walker and his events, U.N. Delegate from Panama George Westerman, Lena Horne in front of the murals, Sammy Davis, Jr. and Norman O. Houston, Robert Kennedy and George A. Beavers, Jr., Joe Lewis, Alex Hailey, Husey Bouie and Sugar Ray Robinson, Larkin Teasley, Brock Peters and Mark Ridley Thomas. Materials also include proof sheets and negatives.
      Box 67-68: Materials include proof sheets and negatives of events and employee head shots.
    - District Office photos, 1961-1990s (Box 68, Box 69, Box 70, Box 71, Box 72)
      Materials are arranged alphabetically by city, region or state and include photographs of employees, executives, building interiors and exteriors, groundbreakings, open houses, paint-ins, meetings, participation with school districts and breakfasts for the following GSM District Offices:
      Box 68: Bakersfield, Century City North 10100, Charlotte, Chicago and Compton.
      Box 69: Dallas, Detroit, Emeryville, Fort Worth, Fresno, GA and Houston.
      Box 70: Los Angeles, L.A. Eastside, Los Angeles Managers, North Carolina, North Texas, Oakland and Oakland East.
      Box 71: Rocky Mountain, Sacramento, San Bernardino and L.A. Eastside, San Diego, San Francisco, Tyler, Vallejo, and Winston-Salem.
      All District Offices photos are arranged alphabetically by department:
      Box 71: Accounting, Administrative Services and Agency.
      Box 72: Auditing, Automatic Debit Accounting, Central Administration, Claims, Data Processing, Federal Credit Union, General Agency, Insurance Administration, Methods and Systems, Personnel, Policy Index, Underwriting and Word Processing.
    - Employee photos, 1940-1995 (Box 73, Box 74, Box 75, Box 76, Box 77)
      Photographs of employees include Home Office and District Office employee head shots arranged alphabetically by last name and images of retired, terminated, award winning, and working employees.
      Box 73: Employee head shots include Arturo Acosta through Henry H. Irumundomon.
      Box 74: Employee head shots include Adrien Jack through Edna Swancy.
      Box 75: Employee head shots include James Tankson through Camille Zenon.
      Box 76: Photographs include images of Lillian Barry, Robert Corral, Thomas Duckett, Earl Jackson, Edgar J. Johnson, Pat Du Rousseau's retirement party, Harold Toliver, Larkin Teasley, Melva Baker, Lorelei Little, James Ward, Wendy Williams, Central Files Department girls on moving day, Thelma Koerber, Relief Baskets for Christmas preparations, Alan Blocker, Norman B. Houston, President Norman O. Houston, William Nickerson, Jr., Verna A. Hickman, Thelma Taylor, Mabel Cleveland, Lucille Ailstock, George A. Beavers, Jr. with Josephine Baker and Councilman Don Allen, the policy index moving day, retired and terminated employees.
      Box 77: Materials include images of retired and terminated employees, staff groups, training sessions, Home Office employees at work, employee of the month, employees from District Offices at work and a Home Office photo album of clerical staff at work as well as Norman O. Houston, Ivan J. Houston, and Helen E. Batiste.
    - Event photos, 1931-2007 (Box 78, Box 79, Box 80, Box 81, Box 82, Box 83, Box 84, Box 85, Box 86, Box 87, Box 88, Box 89, Box 90)
      Event photograph files are arranged chronologically and include local and national events. The following boxes include photographs of events identified by subject.